Finding Aid for University Architect's Office (University of Michigan) Records, ca. 1950-1989.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
University Architect's Office (University of Michigan) records circa 1950-1989
University of Michigan. University Architect's Office.
87288 Bimu B27 2
In-house architectural office of the University of Michigan. Records include project files for new University buildings, and additions to, and alterations of, existing structures; include files for Ann Arbor, Dearborn and Flint sites and off-campus projects with documentation for numerous medical-related buildings; contain minutes, correspondence with University officials, architects and contractors; photographs, brochures and conference notes; also data sheets relating to specific building projects, including cost, size, names of architects and contractors, and construction period.
20 linear feet
3 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were transferred by the University Architect's Office (Donor no. 4810 ) in several accessions, the first received in 1969.
The records are open for research.
The University Architect's Office was established in 1957 within the Plant Service Department. Lynn W. Fry was the first person to hold the title of University Architect. Fry, Supervisor of Plant Extension since 1945 and Supervising Architect since 1948, had gradually assumed an increasing role in the campus's architectural developments as the university rapidly expanded during the post World War II period.
The university administration recognized the need for an organized, planned system to execute the university's building program, and in May 1949 the Regents approved a proposal submitted by the executive officers which included the following provisions (Regents' Proceedings, May 1949, p. 368):
"2. Furthermore, it is believed that the use of a nonresident architectural consultant or consultants should be tried. Such consultants would work with the Regents, the executive officers, the Plant Department, and the Faculty Planning Committee in specifying the general architectural treatment that should be given to a specific building.
3. It is urged that a separate architect be commissioned for each building and that a special building committee for each building work with the architect and the Plant Department in the development of the plans and specifications for the designated building."
Over the years, the university architect has continued to serve as an advisor and liaison between architects and the university community on the many building and renovation projects.
University Architects
1957-1965 Lynn W. Fry
1965-1970 Howard Hakken
1970-1971 Warren E. Poole (Acting)
1971-1972 Richard A. Little
1972-1974 Robert E. Kacel
1974-1993 Richard L. Glissman
1993- Douglas C. Hanna
The records of the University Architect's Office consist of twenty (20) linear feet and three oversize volumes. Records include correspondence, meeting minutes, reports, architectural drawings, and photographs spanning the years from 1950 to 1989. The records document the numerous construction and renovation projects undertaken by the university on the Ann Arbor campus as well as on the Dearborn and Flint campuses. The materials are arranged in two series: University Architects and University Buildings Files. The bulk of the records are comprised of building files
There are three oversize volumes of photographs regarding the Administration Building (LS&A Building), Mary Butler Markley Hall, and the Outpatient Clinic of the University Hospital, which have been removed to an oversize location.
Subjects:
Architects.; Architecture.; Construction industry.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Buildings--Contracts and specifications.; University of Michigan--Campus.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. University Architect's Office.; University of Michigan--Dearborn--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Flint--Buildings.; Dow, Alden B., 1904-1983; Albert Kahn Associates.; Smith, Hinchman & Grylls Associates.; Swanson Associates.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
University of Michigan--Buildings.; Children.; Hospitals--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. University Architect's Office.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; Dormitories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- University Architects
  The University Architects series contains one folder of biographical information about the first University Architect, Lynn W. Fry. Also included are slides of buildings and a photograph of Fry.
  - Lynn W. Fry (includes slides of buildings and photograph of Fry) (Box 1)
- University Buildings Files
  The core series, University Buildings Files, is divided into five subseries: Background Material, Ann Arbor Campus, Dearborn Campus, Flint Campus, and Other Locations. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by name of building or construction project. Folders contain a variety of materials including minutes, correspondence with architectural firms and subcontractors, reports, photographs, cost analyses, and other planning documents. The extent of documentation on a given project varies widely from one building project to another. The records also include material on proposed projects, or parts of projects, that were never realized. These include the Hill Auditorium renovation (pre-2000), Science Building 1, and parts of the Fifty-five Million Dollar Project. For building projects that were completed, there is also information on alternative proposals that were not implemented.
  - Background Material
    The Background Material subseries consists of data sheets about university building projects from the late 1950s to the 1970s. Information on each of the projects include costs, space, names of architects and contractors, and construction period.
    - Data Sheets re: University Building Projects circa 1957-1973 (Box 1)
      (includes cost, size, names of architects and contractors, and construction period)
    - Data Sheets 2 (Box 1)
      (includes development plans and maps, construction costs, building statistics)
  - Ann Arbor Campus
    The largest subseries, Ann Arbor Campus, is divided into seven subsections. Buildings associated with a particular college or school are found under the college or school to which they belonged (i.e., Francois Xavier Bagnoud under Engineering). Medical School buildings are included under the Medical Center subsection rather than within the colleges and schools. Non-medical research facilities such as the Institute for Social Research, are found under the subsection Research Facilities and Institutes. The General Subsection contains information on buildings such as the Administration Building (Fleming), Computing Center, Hill Auditorium, Michigan Union, and recreational and service buildings. The Ann Arbor subseries is organized as follows:
    Colleges and Schools (Boxes 1-7)
    Housing (Box 7)
    Libraries and Archives (Boxes 7-8)
    Medical Center (Boxes 8-15)
    Development and Planning
    Hospitals and Clinics
    Research Facilities and Institutes
    General
    Research Facilities and Institutes (Boxes 15-16)
    Transportation and Parking (Box 16)
    General (Boxes 16-18)
    - Colleges and Schools
      - Architecture and Urban Planning, College of Art and Design, School of
        - Art and Architecture Building
          - General 1966-1974, 3 folders (Box 1)
          - Reports (Box 1)
          - "Building Materials and Construction Systems Study" (Swanson Associates) 1968 (Box 1)
          - "Final Preliminary Design" (Office of Planning) 1970 (Box 1)
          - "Final Preliminary Design" (University Architect's Office) 1970 (Box 1)
          - "Program Analysis and Design Criteria Analysis" (Swanson Associates) February 27, 1969 (Box 1)
          - "The University of Michigan Architecture Building: Report on Planning and Development," 1968 (Box 1)
          - "Utilization of Space Reports," September 8, 1965 (Box 1)
      - Business Administration, School of
        - Addition
          - General 1979-1982, undated (Box 1)
          - Computer Facilities 1980-1982, undated (Box 1)
          - Correspondence
            - Architect 1980-1984 (Box 1)
            - University of Michigan 1977-1982 (Box 1)
            - General 1980-1984 (Box 1)
          - Faculty Offices and Research 1980 (Box 1)
          - Library
            - General 1980-1982 (Box 1)
            - Meeting Minutes 1980 (Box 1)
          - Management Center 1980
            - Meeting Minutes 1979-1982 (Box 1)
            - Report-"Proposed Projects for the Graduate School of Business Administration" (Luckenbach and Ziegelman, Inc.) June 1981 (Box 1)
        - Assembly Hall
          - General 1969-1973, 2 folders (Box 1)
          - Presentation Drawing circa 1970 (Box 1)
          - Report-Architectural Specifications (O'Dell, Hewlett and Luckenbach Associates) 1971 (Box 1)
        - Collaborative Technology Suite 1988-1989 (Box 1)
        - Executive Dormitory
          - General 1983-1984, 1989 (Box 1)
          - Correspondence
            - Architect 1983-1985 (Box 1)
            - University of Michigan 1983-1984 (Box 1)
            - General 1983-1984 (Box 1)
        - Expansion (includes Advanced Management Center) 1965-1969, 1976-1984 (Box 1)
        - Lower Level
          - Correspondence
            - Architect 1985-1989 (Box 1)
            - University of Michigan 1986-1987 (Box 1)
          - General 1986 (Box 1)
        - Renovation
          - General 1984-1987 (Box 2)
          - Correspondence-Architect 1983-1987 (Box 2)
        - Site Plan 1980 (Box 2)
          (includes photographs of the architectural model)
        - William A. Paton Center for Accounting Education and Research
          - General 1972-1976, undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
          - Correspondence
            - Architect 1973-1976, 1980 (Box 2)
            - University of Michigan 1973-1974 (Box 2)
            - General 1974-1976, 1982 (Box 2)
          - Cost Data (Box 2)
          - Meeting Minutes 1972, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
          - Report-"Program Presentation," July 18, 1973 (Box 2)
      - Dentistry, School of
        - General 1954-1974, 3 folders (Box 2)
        - Kellogg Building Remodeling 1964-1968 (Box 2)
        - Photographs of Architectural Model circa 1975 (Box 2)
        - Reports
          - "Additions and Alterations to the School of Dentistry Buildings" (Smith, Hinchman, and Grylls Associates) circa 1964 (Box 2)
          - "Report of Bid Proposal for the Dental Building" (University Architect's Office) 1965 (Box 2)
          - "Outline Specifications for Additions and Alterations to the School of Dentistry Buildings of the University of Michigan" (Smith, Hinchman and Grylls Associates) 1964 (Box 2)
      - Education, School of
        - Rehabilitation 1961-1969 (Box 2)
      - Engineering, College of
        - Aerospace Engineering
          - Aerospace Engineering Building
            - General 1967 (Box 2)
            - Report, "Space Analysis and Minimum Design Criteria" (University Architect's Office) February 28, 1972 (Box 2)
          - Francois-Xavier Bagnoud (FXB) Building
            - Budget 1991 (Box 2)
            - Contract 1990 (Box 2)
            - Correspondence (Box 2)
            - Architect 1989-1991, 2 folders (Box 2)
            - University of Michigan 1989 (Box 2)
            - Regents' Communication 1988-1991 (Box 2)
            - Report-"Prospectus for a New Building for the Department of Aerospace Engineering" (College of Engineering) September 1988 (Box 2)
        - G.G. Brown Building 1983, 1987
          - Building I-A
            - General 1970-1976, 2 folders (Box 3)
            - Presentation Drawing circa 1970s (Box 3)
            - Reports
              - "Architectural Program, Building I" (Swanson Associates) undated (Box 3)
              - "Preliminaries" (Swanson Associates) 1972 (Box 3)
              - "Project Analysis" (Capital Planning) 1971 (Box 3)
          - Building I
            - Clean Room 1983-1986, 2 folders (Box 3)
            - Contract 1984 (Box 3)
            - Correspondence
              - Architect 1982-1990 (Box 3)
              - University of Michigan 1983-1987 (Box 3)
              - General 1975, 1982-1985, 1989 (Box 3)
            - Meeting Minutes 1983-1984 (Box 3)
            - Reports
              - "Architectural Program, Engineering Building I," March 1983, 2 folders (Box 3)
              - "Development Phase" (Smith, Hinchman and Grylls Associates) December 7, 1983 (Box 3)
              - "Program Statement," April 1969 (Box 4)
              - "Schematic Phase report" (Smith. Hinchman and Grylls Associates) July 7, 1983 (Box 4)
              - State of Michigan Negative Declaration; Environmental Impact Statement" (Smith, Hinchman and Grylls Associates) undated (Box 4)
          - Slides-26 color slides of models and drawings undated (Box 4)
        - Building II (Dow Building)
          - Contract 1984 (Box 4)
          - Correspondence
            - Architect 1976-1985, 3 folders (Box 4)
            - State of Michigan 1977-1982 (Box 4)
            - University of Michigan 1975-1985, 1990, 3 folders (Box 4)
            - General 1976-1985, 2 folders (Box 4)
          - Cost Figures 1976-1985 (Box 4)
          - Meeting Minutes 1977-1984, 2 folders (Box 4)
          - Regents' Communication 1984 (Box 4)
          - Reports
            - "Architectural Program: North Campus Instructional Center" (College of Engineering) July 1983 (Box 4)
            - "Development Phase" (Alden B. Dow Associates), July 20,1979 (Box 4)
            - "Economic Feasibility Analysis for the Proposed Run Around Heat Recovery System" (Hoyem-Basso Associates, Inc.) October 12, 1979 (Box 4)
            - "Feasibility Study, Chilled Water Loop System" (Smith, Hinchman and Grylls Associates) March 1, 1984 (Box 4)
            - "Schematic Phase" (Alden B. Dow Associates) February 1979 (Box 4)
            - Untitled (Alden B. Dow Associates) December 5, 1977 (Box 4)
          - University of Michigan Meeting Minutes 1983-1985 (Box 4)
        - Naval Architecture and Marine Engineering Addition
          - General 1977 (Box 4)
          - Correspondence
            - Architect 1977-1978 (Box 4)
            - General 1975-1978 (Box 4)
          - Meeting Minutes 1977-1978 (Box 4)
          - Report, "Preliminaries" (Swanson Associates) April 5, 1977 (Box 4)
        - Engineering Complex
          - Reports
            - "Faculty Requirement for Office and Laboratory Building North Campus" (College of Engineering) August 1959 (Box 4)
            - "Site and Building Plans for an Engineering and Technological Center" (North Campus Planning Committee) June 1967 (Box 4)
            - "The University of Michigan Engineering Complex Study" (Swanson Associates) June 15, 1975, 2 volumes (Box 4)
        - Structures Laboratory Building 1966 (Box 4)
      - Law School
        - General 1967, 1971-1981, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Correspondence-Architect 1973-1981 (Box 5)
        - Meeting Minutes 1974-1977 (Box 5)
        - Report, "Pre-Design Architectural Study for a New Addition to the Law School, University of Michigan" (Brown/Steele/Bos) October 19, 1973 (Box 5)
      - Literature, Science, and the Arts, College of (LS & A)
        - Administration Building
          - Photograph album undated (Box 5)
          - Photograph album, "Sculptural Designs, Administration Building" (Marshall Fredericks, sculptor) (Volume 1)
            (located at B-166-4)
        - Chemistry Building
          - Report-"Preliminary Program Statement: General Science Facilities Remodeling," January 17, 1969 (Box 5)
        - History of Art Facility
          (see also Tappan Hall)
          - General 1971-1973 (Box 5)
          - Report
            - "Feasibility Studies for Providing a Solution to the Space Problems of the History of Art Department" (University Architect's Office) May 31, 1973 (Box 5)
        - Kraus (E.H.) Natural Science Building
          - Correspondence
            - Architect 1975-1990 (Box 5)
            - University of Michigan 1970-1991 (Box 5)
            - General 1987-1989 (Box 5)
          - Meeting Minutes 1975-1981, 1987 (Box 5)
          - Reports
            - "Feasibility Study" (Colvin Robinson Associates) undated (Box 5)
            - "Feasibility Study Update (Holman/Meneghini/Overhiser) September 25, 1985 (Box 5)
            - "Preliminary Design Report" (Holman/Meneghini/Overhiser) November 14, 1986 (Box 5)
            - "Preliminary Program Statement," January 17, 1969 (Box 5)
            - "Renovation Required in the Natural Science Building," December 1968 (Box 5)
            - "Schematic Renovation Plan" (Herrman and Holman) February 1982, 2 volumes (Box 5)
        - Modern Languages Building
          - General 1964-1969, 2 folders (Box 5)
          - General 1969-1975 (Box 6)
          - Photographs and Negatives of Office and Site Plans undated (Box 6)
          - Reports
            - "Final Preliminary Presentation" (University Architect's Office) October 18, 1965 (Box 6)
            - "Preliminary Specifications and Schedule of Finishes" (Albert Kahn Associates) June 15, 1965 (Box 6)
            - "Program Statement," November 11, 1965 (Box 6)
            - "A Random-Access Multiple-Program System for the U of M Language Laboratory" (David L. Mills) August 1965 (Box 6)
            - "Revised Schematics," May 1967 (Box 6)
            - "Schematic Planning Stage," June 14, 1968 (Box 6)
            - "Schematic Presentation" (University Architect's Office) June 15, 1965 (Box 6)
        - Physics and Astronomy Building
          - Correspondence 1971-1972 (Box 6)
          - Report, "Preliminary Specifications and Schedule of Finishes" (Albert Kahn Associates) October 26, 1960 (Box 6)
        - Randall Laboratory
          - Report--"Addition to Randall Laboratory Building" (Albert Kahn Associates) January 15, 1957 (Box 6)
        - Science Building 1
          - Report, "A Preliminary Proposal for a Science Building I," October 1968 (Box 6)
        - Tappan Hall
          - Addition 1981-1983, 1987 (Box 6)
          - Undergraduate Astronomy Center, Project Analysis 1971 (Box 6)
      - Public Health, School of
        - General 1962-1971, 5 folders (Box 6)
        - Reports
          - "General Contract Work Specifications" (Albert Kahn Associates) 1968, 3 volumes (Box 6)
          - "Final Design Analysis Report" (Albert Kahn Associates) January 19, 1968 (Box 6)
          - "Final Preliminary Presentation" (University Architect's Office) July 5, 1967 (Box 6)
          - "Outline Specifications" (Albert Kahn Associates) May 12, 1966 (Box 6)
          - "Outline Specifications" (Albert Kahn Associates) June 30, 1966 (Box 6)
          - "Outline Specifications and Design Analysis Report" (Albert Kahn Associates) April 10 1967 (Box 6)
          - "Preliminary Evaluation of Alternate Sites" (Albert Kahn Associates) November 8, 1965 (Box 7)
          - "Preliminary Program" (University Architect's Office) January 12, 1965 (Box 7)
          - "Schematic Presentation" (University Architect's Office), April 7,1966 (Box 7)
          - "School of Public Health Addition" (Lewis J. Sarvis) December 24, 1956 (Box 7)
          - "Space Proration Tables for Final Submission In" (Albert Kahn Associates) January 12, 1968 (Box 7)
          - "School of Public Health Addition: Application for Joint Construction Grant"
            - June 30, 1966, 2 volumes (Box 7)
            - July 22, 1966, 2 volumes (Box 7)
      - Rackham School of Graduate Studies-Rackham Building
        - Report-"Study of Remodeling Main Auditorium" (Smith, Hinchman and Grylls Associates) January 1960 (Box 7)
      - Housing
        - Vera Baits Housing, Stairwell Enclosure 1969 (Box 7)
        - Bursley Hall
          - Report-"North Campus Residence Hall" (Swanson Associates) December 16, 1957 (Box 7)
        - Mary Butler Markley Hall
          - Photograph Album (Volume 2)
          - Photographs of building exterior 1960s (Box 7)
        - Northwood IV
          - General 1963-1975, 2 folders (Box 7)
          - Photographs and Negatives of Construction undated (Box 7)
          - Reports
            - "Final Preliminary Presentation" (University Architect's Office) September 7, 1966 (Box 7)
            - "Schematic Presentation" (University Architect's Office) July 25, 1966 (Box 7)
        - Northwood V
          - General 1968-1972 (Box 7)
          - Report, "Specifications for the Construction of Site Grading and Roadways, Sewers and Water Mains, Electrical Work for the Regents of the University of Michigan" (McNamee, Porter and Seeley) October 19, 1970 (Box 7)
        - Nu Sigma Nu Fraternity House 1966-1970 (Box 7)
        - Residential College / East Quad 1967-1970, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Libraries and Archives
      - Bentley Historical Library/Michigan Historical Collections
        - Addition 1979-1980 (Box 7)
        - Construction 1964-1973, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - Floyd Starr Room 1976-1977 (Box 7)
        - Report, "Specifications for Landscape Development" (Beckett Jackson Raeder) undated (Box 7)
      - Clements Library
        - Air Conditioning 1969 (Box 7)
      - Gerald R. Ford Library
        - Color photograph of building exterior undated (Box 7)
      - General Library Renovation
        - General 1965-1975, 3 folders (Box 8)
        - Reports
          - "General Library Renovations: Report on Planning and Development," 1968 (Box 8)
          - "Preliminary Planning Documents" (Albert Kahn Associates) November 30, 1972 (Box 8)
          - "Schematic Presentation" (Engineering Services) July 1965 (Box 8)
      - Harlan Hatcher Graduate Library Addition
        - General 1963-1970, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Photographs 1966 (Box 8)
        - Reports
          - "Preliminary Site Plan Study for a Central Campus Library" (Albert Kahn Associates) 1963 (Box 8)
          - "Review of Samples, Bids, and Specifications of Library Stacks and Lockers" (University Library) 1967 (Box 8)
          - "Revised Outline Specifications and Schedule of Finishes" (Albert Kahn Associates) 1965 (Box 8)
      - Schoenberg Archives (School of Music)
        - General 1971 (Box 8)
        - Photographs of Architectural Model undated (Box 8)
    - Medical Center
      - Development and Planning
        - General 1960-1961 (Box 8)
        - Planning and Planning Coordinator 1965-1969 (Box 8)
        - Planning Committee-Minutes 1969-1970 (Box 8)
      - Reports
        - Electrical and Mechanical; Services
          - "The Electrical Renovation for the University of Michigan Medical Center," undated (Box 8)
          - "Report on Electrical and Mechanical Services Continuation in the Medical Center Area" (Cummins and Bernard Inc.) (Box 8)
          - "Graphic Signing Study," undated (Box 8)
          - "Medical Center Building Commitments: Summary of Medical Center Building Commitments and Major Renovation for Existing Structures" (Office of Planning, University of Michigan Medical Center) December 1970 (Box 8)
          - "Medical Center Planning Report: A Guide to Future Physical Development" (Johnson, Johnson and Roy) 1961 (Box 8)
          - "Physical Facilities Planning Guide: Medical Center Planning Report," 1967 (Box 8)
          - "A Strategy for Renewal: A Progress Report of Long Range Medical Center Planning with Special Emphasis on the Problems of Clinical Resources" (University of Michigan Medical Center) May 1973 (Box 8)
          - "University of Michigan Medical Center" (Skidmore, Owings, and Merrill) undated (Box 8)
          - "University of Michigan Medical Center: Working Draft of Long Range Plan," October 1972 (Box 8)
      - Hospitals and Clinics
        - W.K. Kellogg Eye Center